Guide to the Collection on Enslavement in Cuba MSS.569
Fales Library and Special Collections
Collection on Enslavement in Cuba
1809-1898
Fales Library and Special Collections
Fales Library
MSS.569
2 linear foot in 2 flat boxes
The time period covered by this collection was the final century of 400 years of Spanish colonization of the island of Cuba. Although Spain and Great Britain agreed to end the trade of enslaved people in Spanish colonies by 1820, an estimated one million enslaved Africans were brought to Cuba by Spanish colonists. Cuba formally ended its participation in the Transatlantic Slave Trade in 1867, and abolished the legal enslavement of people in 1886. Enslaved people endured family separation, harsh manual labor on sugar plantations and in sugar mills, and labor within an enslaver's household. Enslaved women were often victims of sexual assault and exploitation. From 1847-1874, hundreds of thousands of Chinese men were trafficked to Cuba as indentured laborers by the Spanish, French, British, and Americans. This collection consists of documents concerning slavery in Spanish-colonized Cuba between 1809 and 1898, and the infrastructure that supported Spanish and American planation owners at the expense of enslaved and indentured individuals. Materials include telegrams, contracts, identification papers, travel licenses, birth notices, marriage and baptism records, death and burial certificates, purchase and insurance documents, and manumission records documenting various aspects of enslavement in Cuba, including the economics of the Transatlantic Slave Trade, demographics of Cuban populations, England's abolition of slavery, the transportation of indentured Chinese laborers to Cuba, family relationships in the context of slavery, living and working conditions on sugar cane plantations, and manumission processes.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of documents concerning slavery in Spanish-colonized Cuba between 1809 and 1898 and the infrastructure that supported Spanish and American planation owners at the expense of enslaved and indentured individuals. Materials include telegrams, contracts, identification papers, travel licenses, birth notices, marriage and baptism records, death and burial certificates, purchase and insurance documents, and manumission records documenting various aspects of enslavement in Cuba, including the economics of the Transatlantic Slave Trade, demographics of Cuban populations, England's abolition of slavery, the transportation of indentured Chinese laborers to Cuba, family relationships in the context of slavery, living and working conditions on sugar cane plantations, and manumission processes.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection were purchased from bookseller Kevin Jackson by Timothy V. Johnson, NYU Librarian for Africana Studies, Anthropology and Food Studies in December 2014; original provenance is unknown. The collection was transferred to the Fales Library and Special Collections in 2017. The accession number associated with this purchase is 2019.010.
Separated Materials
Folder 1 in the inventory, a grouping of 80 documents concerning a case of five enslaved people at a sugar mill who killed a man they believed to be the Governor General of Cuba, was removed from the collection and cataloged separately as HV6535.C9 C66 1842.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the seller.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Iron gall ink present in many documents in the collection has caused paper loss. Some documents are partially legible as a result.
Historical Note
The time period covered by this collection was the final century of 400 years of Spanish colonization of the island of Cuba. Although Spain and Great Britain agreed to end the trade of enslaved people in Spanish colonies by 1820, an estimated one million enslaved Africans were brought to Cuba by Spanish colonists. Cuba formally ended its participation in the Transatlantic Slave Trade in 1867, and abolished the legal enslavement of people in 1886. Enslaved people endured family separation, harsh manual labor on sugar plantations and in sugar mills, and labor within an enslaver's household. Enslaved women were often victims of sexual assault and exploitation. From 1847-1874, hundreds of thousands of Chinese men were trafficked to Cuba as indentured laborers by the Spanish, French, British, and Americans. In port cities like Hong Kong and Macao, Chinese men were kidnapped or coerced into signing contracts by enslavers posing as recruitment agents. Although the contracts offered freedom after eight years, this freedom was not enforced, and the laborers often died before the term ended due to malnourishment and abusive conditions.
Slave trade -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Slavery -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Slavery -- Economic aspects -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Slavery -- Social aspects -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Foreign workers, Chinese -- Cuba.; Chinese -- Cuba -- History -- 19th century.; Vital statistics records; Free papers; Enslaved Persons; Spain -- Colonies; Forced labor -- Cuba
- Cuban Manuscript Concerning the Incarceration of Self-Liberated Cimarrones, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Cuban Telegram Regarding Human Trafficking and Slavery, August 1857 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Scope and Contents
  This Cuban telegram regarding human trafficking and slavery was sent to Lieutenant Governor General Cardenas.
- Death Certificate for Estanislao, an Enslaved Chinese Man, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  According to the death certificate, Estanislao died at Charity Hospital of San Felipe y Santiago.
- Insurance Certificate for a Person Enslaved by Joaquin Soler, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  This certificate, created by La Protectora Compania General Cubana de Seguros Mutuos Sobre la Vida de Esclavos, includes information such as the price of the insurance, the corresponding legal articles, and the signature of the insurance director. It does not appear to include the name of the enslaved person.
- Certificates of Burial for a Fetus, August 7, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  These certificates of burial were issued by the Church of the Holy Spirit and the Church of Monserrate in Havana. They do not appear to list the name of the deceased, whose mother was an enslaved person.
- Document Summarizing Enslaved Person Expenditures, 1818-1819 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- La Providencia Insurance Document for an Enslaved Person in Havana, 1859-09-30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Document of Marriage Between Enslaved People, 1816-12-11-1816-12-12 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Sobre Desobediencia Negro Cargador de Cadaveres, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Identity Paper for Dominga, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Dominga was a 21 year old enslaved woman.
- Identity Paper for Geronimo Ganga, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Manumission Document for Lelicia Frenyo, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Burial Document of an Enslaved Person, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Baptism Document for Francisco Herrera, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Manumission Document for Rosa Delgado, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- La Protectora Insurance Receipt for an Enslaved Person, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Insurance receipt issued in Havana by the Director General to D. Franco Equileor regarding the purchase of an enslaved person.
- Telegram concerning the persecution of trading enslaved people by the Lieutenant Governor of Cuba, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Judicial Deposit of Enslaved People, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- La Protectora Insurance Receipt for an Enslaved Person, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Stamped Document for Renting Out an Enslaved Person, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Legal Agreement Regarding Deposit of Francisco Carabali, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- La Providencia Receipt for Insurance of Enslaved People, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Receipt for payment of La Providencia insurance purchased by enslaver Francisco Munso.
- Identification Paper for Guillermo Ceta, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Government identification paper permitting the travel of Guillermo Ceta, a man enslaved by Cristobal Alonzo of La Habana, to Pueblo.
- Memo on the Receipt of Muzzles in Cienfuegos, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Short note describing the receipt of muzzles in Cienfuegos, from Habana.
- Marriage Contract between Two Enslaved People, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Telegram to Captain Pral from Francisco F. de la Regeas, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Telegram sent to Captain Pral in Habana from Francisco F. de la Regeas concerning legal statues in Santo Domingo.
- Marriage Contract between Two Enslaved People, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- La Providencia Receipt for Insurance of Enslaved People, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Receipt for payment of La Providencia insurance purchased by enslaver Ambrosio M. Rendon.
- Marriage Contract between Two Emancipated People, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Marriage contract between Francisco Andrade and Moxcelenia (?) Avinev, both free people.
- Telegram Concerning Enslavement from Ramon Menduinal, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Documents Regarding the Death and Burial of Felix, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Felix, a criollo man enslaved by Juan Delgado, drowned in a well in 1854. Felix was 30 years old.
- Correspondence regarding the grave of Felix, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Document Referencing the Emancipation of Marmelita, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Birth Notice of Jose, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Certificate of Indenture for Chinese Laborer Anselmo, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  This document states that Anselmo, a 23-year-old laborer from China, was contracted to work in a quarry for eight years and for Carmen Herrera for an equal amount of time.
- Contract Enslaving Franc Real, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  La Comision Poblacion Blanca contract regarding Franc Real, a 20 year old man from Palma, Spain, who was enslaved by Aburo S.
- Contract Enslaving Justo Asioca, June 1868 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Tenencia de Gobierno de Guanajay contract regarding Justo Asioca, a 28 year old Chinese man who was enslaved by Andres Fin.
- Contract Enslaving Enreterio San Achin, May 1868 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  Tenencia de Gobierno de Guanajay contract regarding Enreterio San Achin, a 28 year old Chinese man who was enslaved by Paulino Sigarreta.
- Document of the Death and burial of Domingo, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  According to the document, Domingo was an enslaved Chinese man.
- Contract Enslaving Julien Aguat, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  Gobierno Politico de la Habana contract regarding Julien Aguat, a 28 year old Chinese man who was enslaved by Manuel Dorado.
- Identification Document for Leopoldo, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  Gobierno Politico de la Habana identification document regarding Leopoldo, a 24 year old Chinese man who was enslaved by B. Pereda.
- Contract Enslaving nine Spanish people, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  Real Junta de Fomento de la Isla de Cuba contract regarding nine Spanish people who were enslaved by Saypa Hernandez: Jose Hernandez, his wife Bernarda, Luyor, Antonio, Maxie, Gregorio, Novento Luis Garcia, Art Calaturo Luyo, and Salvatore Inan Reiz.
- Document Regarding Enslaved People Who Escaped from a Ship, August 1842 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Biographical Note
  Jerónimo Valdés (1784–1855) was a Spanish military figure and administrator. Born in Villarín, in Asturias, he participated in the battle of Ayacucho (1824), which was a defeat for the Spanish. He served as Viceroy of Navarre from 1833 to 1834 and also served as Minister of War. He fought on the Liberal (Isabeline) side in the First Carlist War. Valdés lost the Battle of Artaza (April 22, 1835). Valdés signed the Lord Eliot Convention soon after, regulating the treatment of prisoners during that war. He later served as captain-general of Valencia, and of Galicia, and served as governor of Cuba from 1841 to September 1843.
  This printed memo was issued by the Captain General of Cuba, Geronimo Valdes. It accounts that there was an illegal disembarkation of escaped enslaved people who hid in a farm near Matanzas. Valdes also states that this information was passed on by the British.
- Documentation Regarding Sale of the La Constancia Sugar Mill and List of 72 Enslaved People, 1856-02-16 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  List of people enslaved by Yugo la Costancia: Bernardo of Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone); Fernando; José Maria; Domingo; José Maria; Antonio; Ysidro; Ramon; Miguel; Alesandro; Nicolas; Juan Banta(?); Pablo; Martin; José de la Luz; Julian; Pascual; José de Jesus; Juaquin of Minia; Manuel; Caruelo of Macua; Gerbasio; Facundo(?); Rafael of Congo; Domingo; Antonio Peria; Reniger from Criullo; Luis; Cristobal; Rogue; Eusebio (?); José del Rosario; Juan; Sernan of Criullo; Abraham; Loreto; Juaquin; Candelario; Salustiano; Miguel; [illegible name] of Mata; Eugenia; Fernando; G~; Antonio; Hilario; Regino; Carlos; Juliana of Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone); Josefa; Antonia; Paula; Matilde; Maria de Jesus of Conga; Vitoria of Mina; A~; Catalina; Vicenta of Carabali; Pasilia of Criolla; Barbara; Ynés; Petrona; [illegible name]; Ana Ma; Luisa; Eulogia; Marcelina of Criolla; Lacarido; Ynes, Rosa.
- Priest's Formal Declaration of Baptism of a Freed Person, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Contract in Guanajay between Felis Banbul and Laborer Vicente Vega from China, 1868-05-26 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  Government Department of Guanajay, Felis Banbul, entered into a contract with 28 year old laborer Vicente Vega from Canton (China) for two years. According to the contract, Vega was to be paid a salary of eight pesos.
- Cuban License Giving Permission for Four Congolese Enslaved People to Travel by Train, 1845-10-12 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  Enslaved people listed are: Petro from Criolla; Jose Lucumi; Cristobal from Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone); and Florence from Congo. Document is signed by Governor Leopold O'Donnell.
- Cuban License Giving Permission for 36 Enslaved People to Travel by Train, 1845-10-31 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  Cuban license to travel freely by train to work on a sugar plantation. Enslaved people include: Antonio from Criollo; Jerman; Fran; Camilo; Hepomuceno; Cirito; Domingo; Polomo; Francisco; Prospero from Criolla; Isidro; Miguel from Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone); Matilde; Canuta; Ynes; [illegible name]; [illegible name]; Serefina; Ma Fran; Dominga; Joaquina from Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone); M. de la Cruz; Andrea; Ignasia; Francisca from Carabali; Damiana; Gregoria from Conga; and Julia. Document is signed by Governor Leopoldo O'Donnell.
- Document from Spanish Officials to Cuban Government Regarding Fine for Enslavers of Escaped Enslaved People, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  Document was written in Aranjuez, Spain during the Presidencia del Consejo de Ministerio de Ultramar and addressed to the Captain General of Cuba Domingo Dulce y Garay, who signed it upon receipt in Havana. The document discusses a fine of 30 pesos for owners of escaped enslaved people.
- Labor Contract Issued for Felipe Alvansa Lorano and Dolores Cantillo, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Labor Contract issued for 28 Enslaved People, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  Enslaved people include A. Hareia Perez, Ignacio Perez Martin, Cabrera de la Cairr, Domingo Lopes de Soper, Juan Medina, Augustin Martin Sandia, Foreana Guerra Hermand, Algio Acona, Juan Remedia Rodrig, Juan Delgado Pino, Nicolas Sanchez, Juan Ventura, Jore Rodrig, Jore Gabriel Ortega, Clemente Perez Hernand, Ynidao Entrella Bentigra, Lucious de la Coneff Eponiso, Juan de la C. Bello, Augustus de la C. Bello, Jore Hernandez, Portifo Luis Sanchez, Perez Martin, Viciente Diaz, Franco Perez, Mateo Carpio, Jore Manuel Remedio, and Geronimo Hernand.
- Identity Paper for Luis, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Neighborhood News Bulletin on a Freedperson who was Subsequently robbed, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Baptismal Declaration for Luis from Congo and Ricardo from Macau, Enslaved by Alejandro de Castro, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Birth declaration for Miguel Pripo [sp?], Born to Freewoman Oqueda Valdes, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Declaration Attesting that Juan Nacion Lucunne [sp?] Enslaved by Dr. Pedro Martin Prabell and his Godfather Alejo was Enslaved by Dr. Jose Calasano Bilardebo, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Birth Notice for the Child of Two Enslaved people, Nestor and Ramona, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  The document indicates that the father, Nestor, is from the Congo and the mother, Ramona, is from Ganga (now known as Sierra-Leone).
- Request to Have a Newborn Child of an Enslaved Woman and Unnamed Man Baptized., 1852 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Statement of baptism for a Congolese enslaved person who belongs to the "Commission of the Railroad", 1836 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Manuscript Concerning the Capture of Escaped Enslaved People, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  The document concerns the escape and capture of Luis, an enslaved person from the Congo, and Inastasio, another enslaved person. Their enslaver was Dolores Pebles de Pimienta.
- Declaration that the Sacred Sacrement is Being Given to a Enslaved Native Person, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  The enslaved person is described as criollo.
- Birth Notice for the Child of an Enslaved Mother, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Birth Notice for Merced Candelaria, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  This document describes the birth of Merced Candelaria on February 2, 1847. Merced's parents were both enslaved people.
- Statement on Martina Abasi of Carabali, 1860s (Box 2, Folder 65)
  Martina Abasi, a free woman of color, is identified as the godmother of emancipated people.
- Birth Notice of the Child of Juana Albarez, 1850s (Box 2, Folder 66)
  Note on the birth of the child of Juana Albarez, a free woman of color, on All Saints Day. The child is the grandchild of Antonio Albarez and Rosalia Carrora, also free people of color, and the godchild of Anselmo Garcia and Sabel Angel, both identified as criollo. The father is unknown.
- Birth Notice of Maria Manuela, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  Note on the birth of Maria Manuela, January 1877, to Emilia Dias (born Guines), maternal grandmother Eusebia Dias, and godmother Dominga Valdes.
- Baptism Notice of Pastoria, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  Notice of the baptism of Pastoria, a criolla child born on March 30, 1862 into enslavement. She is the daughter of Polonia, a criolla woman, and an unknown father. Both parents were enslaved by Ygnacio do Oildosola. The godmother of the child is Ascunsion, a criolla woman enslaved by Josefa de Osmal.
- Birth Notice of Serafin Usvano de Jesus, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  Notice of the birth of Serafin Usvano de Jesus on May 25, 1862 in Habana. A signed statement follows declaring that José Congo, an emancipated Congolese person, the godchild of an enslaved person, has been in the custody of Colonel D. Antonio Garcia Rizo since seventeen years of age.
- Neighborhood News Bulletin Describing a Fight, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  Manuscript news bulletin discussing a fight between two enslaved persons from different enslavers.
- Birth Notice of Laurecia, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  Notice of the birth of Laurencia, daughter of Nicenta, a criolla woman, and an unknown father who was enslaved by J. Godinez. The child's godmother is Maria Mincheta, a criolla woman enslaved by Sofia Perran.
- Manuscript Concerning Two Enslaved People Not Listed on Ship Manifest, Undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
  Manuscript concerning two enslaved people named Ines and Raimunda not listed on ship manifest.
- Birth Notice of Arnalda, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  Notice of the birth of Arnalda, a criolla girl. Arnalda is the daughter of Nestor from the Congo and Ramona from Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone), both enslaved by Leon de Martiarte. Her godmother is Mariane.
- Manuscript Concerning an Emancipated Congolese Person Pursued by Law Enforcement, 1846 (Box 2, Folder 74)
- Emancipation Document, 1886 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  Emancipation document for five people, named: Guadalupe, Silvestre, Ricardo, Ruperto, and Eduardo.
- Manumission Document for Higinio Guillermo, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  Manumission document for Higinio Guillermo, a boy in Habana born to an enslaved woman named Juana Paula. Higinio Guillermo's father is not named.
- Death Certificate for Domingo, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  Death certificate for Domingo, a man described as an escaped enslaved person originally from Asia. Domingo died at the Hospital de Caridad de San Felipe y Santiago.
- Emancipation Document, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  Emancipation document for five people, named: Niealasa, Valentin, Gregoria, Luisa, and Maltida. The document also lists Matilda's daughter Perfecta.
- Notice that an Emancipated Man was seen in a Havana Warehouse, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 79)
- Birth Notice of Angel, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 80)
- Birth Notice of Maria Micaela Garcia, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 81)
- Birth Notice of Fran. and Beatriz, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 82)
- Birth Notice of Maria Ca[mdel]aria, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 83)
- Birth Notice, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  This document is a birth notice of a child who was likely enslaved.
- Notice of a Sighting of the Goleta [schooner] Aurelia Feliz, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 85)
- Manuscript of Priest Presenting Two Criados for Domestic Labor, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 86)